[music]
>> Welcome to a busy central launch edition
2026 release wave one and welcome to
this session what's new in e-documents.
My name is Alexander Totovic. I'm
product manager and today I will
together with my colleague Magnus show
all these nice news in this area.
So first we'll go technically. I will
explain what is new. Uh
this is important be made redesign of
PEPPOL format.
So now we extended this from base app
and PEPPOL is now first party app.
This is much easier for more control,
more scalability, easier for
localizations and other customizations.
So this is only technically.
But what else about functionalities?
One new functionality really important
link inbound e-documents to purchase
invoice and this is extremely important
when you have the such a problem. You
have intercompany configured. Imagine it
and now both of companies have
obligation to report through e-documents
to some network. So first company A will
prepare sales invoice and send to the
PEPPOL provider for example
and in the same time in a background
system will create intercompany purchase
invoice in the company B.
So now we have created invoice in
company B
but we will receive through PEPPOL
network another electronic invoice and
we cannot connect them.
So this is a problem.
At this time we couldn't do it.
We could use we can receive only to
collector but we couldn't connect. So it
was a problem.
And solution is that now you can easily
link already created purchase invoice so
created by an intercompany or
differently you have purchase invoice
create already created in the system.
You can link with a received e-invoice
through some of
course there are some rules about
amounts and so on but you will see this
in a demo.
What else?
Um
We have let's say set of smaller
features in localization. So I will just
show you what is the most important and
you will see all these small things in
the demos.
First now we have default e-documents
type on the vendor templates. You know
that you can choose if default option is
purchase invoice or purchase order. Now
you can prepare on vendor templates and
it will be applied to all vendors
created from this template. We also have
service participant
linked to company information. Earlier
we had service participant only to
customer vendors but now you have
company information. So
we can be much easier and much more
compliant with some local regulations.
We enabled payment
with e-documents. This is mostly
required in French localization but this
is as a functionality enabled in a
framework and we deliver and we work a
lot of localizations.
We enabled verify tool in Spain. Now
this is a public preview but this is
completed. This is a public preview only
because this is not enforced to be used
yet and we have some period where you
can test and if you have some feedback
you will send to us so we can eventually
improve.
Uh additional we enabled e-invoicing in
Denmark OIOUBL format to work together
with carbon footprint. So now when you
send financial details through
electronic invoicing you can send a
carbon footprint as well and you can
read both of them and automatically
populate all carbon footprint
information in your purchase invoice.
And work in progress French electronic
invoicing. This is something what we are
working on. You can find much more
details in our release plan but it will
be already in on a time.
Okay now Magnus you can show all these
demos.
Thanks Alexander. So let's see the new
PEPPOL app that we have shipped as a
first party app instead of having it in
base app.
Before we dive into Business Central I
thought I would actually for the
developers out there just show
BC apps our repository where we have all
the code.
Um specifically so you can understand
how you should extend and use this new
app.
So here on my screen I have opened up
our BC apps repository and you can see
now that under apps W1
we have this new folder called PEPPOL
where we have both the app and the tests
related to to the W1 PEPPOL application.
And specifically for you you might find
it interesting to go and see the
extensibility examples and I thought I
would open those up so we can just take
a brief look
cuz it explains how you should as a
developer or as a consultant uh extend
or utilize the extensibility in the app
to build your own version or build that
for your requirements in
your country.
So here we can see if we just take a a
brief look
that the PEPPOL app app exposes 10
interfaces which is
quite some but they're divided into the
different parts of the format and here
you can see that we now have the PEPPOL
3.0 format enum that you then
can
use and and extend and there will be an
example here as you can see. So you just
take a dependency on the app.
Then there is an explanation of all the
different formats
document information for instance or
line information
so on and so forth. Each form each
interface is a is a specific part of the
format as I said. So you don't have to
change everything in the format. You can
pick out specific parts of it that you
need adjust it.
So let's take a look. For instance here
we can have in our application if we're
building one we can do an enum extension
and then we can just provide a new value
just as you know it uh how you extend uh
enums and here you can then provide
specific implementations.
For instance I have my own validation
because I have custom fields in in in my
app source app that I want to validate
before actually creating
a PEPPOL format.
Um and as you can see just PEPPOL
validation interface
has all these procedures that you would
then have to go and and implement and
there even is an example of you know my
PEPPOL validation.
And here you can see that we for
instance said that there is some custom
logic that you could add here just as a
sample for you to understand.
So this hopefully should make it very
straightforward for you
to to go out and and maybe have to
adjust and this is a change that's
different from you know the
let's say old way of extending through
events because this allows you to have
multiple different um types of
PEPPOL let's say because you can have
you know multiple apps that actually
extend the enum and then select which
one you need.
So this is more how we build
extensibility nowadays and this is a
good example for you to also go and
learn from.
So if I just jump into BC
and now if you
search and tell me for PEPPOL
you'll see that there now is a PEPPOL
3.0 setup that you can actually open
just a small page where you can then
select the specific enum value that you
have added
with your custom
code. And you can see that it defaults
to sales and
service
and this is exactly the same as it used
to be in base app. It's just moved
essentially.
And just as an example some of you might
have been using this electronic document
formats
um which were an ability to you know
when you post a sales invoice you could
then create a actual physical file using
the the base app implementation of
PEPPOL. Now there there is additional
entries which is for the first party app
and this is because that
we're going to
the plan is to obsolete the code and
remove it from base app so it only lives
in the first party app and at some point
later on
this electronic document formats are
also being phased out because now you
know you can set the same thing up with
with e-documents. So of course the first
party app will also be uptaken um by
e-documents.
All right. Let's look at the next thing
which is the ability to link inbound
e-documents to existing purchase
invoices.
And this is ability we've added
specifically for the new draft page in
the documents because in certain
scenarios when you're using intercompany
you could have already received a
purchase invoice through intercompany
and at the same time also get
an invoice through your connector and
now you have
essentially duplicate right? So we'll
see how instead of you know creating a
new purchase invoice you can just link
to the existing one.
And to show this
I will open up the inbound e-document
page.
And here you can see I have a an example
that we will open.
And right now
there is actually no vendor selected so
I'll go ahead and just choose one.
And the specific thing about this
feature is that it it's currently only
allowed for intercompany vendors.
So
once this is done vendor 10000 is not an
intercompany and if you then go to
actions where this new ability is this
link to existing document if we click
that you'll see that the IC partner code
must be set in in vendor 10000 and it's
not because it's not an intercompany
vendor so you're not allowed to do that
and that is by design.
So to fix that let's actually change to
a vendor that is an intercompany vendor.
And we will use Cronus
uh IC 1020
as one of our demo data vendors here.
And now,
if I go to the same action again,
because this is actually the document
that you receive through the connector
is matched to a vendor that is set up
with intercompany,
you now have the ability to link to
existing document.
And here you can see that it actually
shows the list.
The important thing here is that, of
course, it only filters down invoices
that is specific to the vendor, but also
that the amount corresponds to the total
on the invoice. So, let me actually just
show you that.
So, if you go to purchase invoices,
you can see that this specific invoice
is here, and we can open it up.
And on the document including that, this
number
176.43
has to match what was received through
the connector, otherwise we won't allow
you to
to link them. So, if for instance, I
just put a one in front here,
and then we go back,
and we again click this process link to
existing document,
it is no longer showing up, and that is
by design. So, just be aware that, you
know, the totals have to match, which
makes
a lot of sense.
So,
just
quickly jumping back and forth here to
just undo what I just did.
Yes, setting back the document amount
just to 176.43,
and we just go back.
We can now actually choose the the
document, so let's try that.
If we click okay,
and you are asked if you want to link,
we'll say yes.
And now you can see that
we actually go to the to the invoice,
because the process of the incoming
document is actually done. It is
processed, and if we go back just to to
actually show you that, you can see here
that the draft is now processed. It is
linked to this specific document, and
you don't have to, you know, it won't
create a new one.
And that's it for for being able to link
to existing purchase documents.
All right, and that is how you can link
an inbound e-document to an existing
purchase invoice. You can see a lot of
interesting links you can follow, you
can find important information there, or
you can subscribe on LinkedIn. Please do
it to be updated with all new, nice,
interesting information coming directly
from Microsoft, and of course, YouTube
channel where you can find all these BC
LE videos from this release, from
previous releases, and some other
recordings as well.
So, thank you for watching this video,
and I hope you will not be disappointed
with all new features in e-documents.